Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. London Office. New business records, 1946-1998 and undated RL.11670
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. London Office. New business records
1946-1998 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. London Office
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
RL.11670
8.0 Linear Feet
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. It is headquartered in New York. The London Office first opened in 1899. Collection includes correspondence, policy manuals, presentation texts and designs and other printed materials that document JWT new business proposals for commercial, nonprofit and governmental institutions. Some of the proposals include marketing plans for flotation and privatization of nationalized industries. Companies represented include Barclays Bank, British Airways, British Rail, BUPA (British United Provident Association), Cancer Relief Macmillan Fund, CGL (Computer Games Limited), De Beers, Dunlop, Esso, Findus, Gatwick Airport, H.P. Bulmer, ICI Dulux, ITVA, Jaguar, Kodak, NatWest and Philips, as well as British governmental agencies including the Central Office of Information (later COI Communications), Home Office and Metrication Board. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: General Files; Prospect Files.
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. It is headquartered in New York. The London Office first opened in 1899.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Company. London Office. New business records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1998-2008.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
J. Walter Thompson Company. London Office. Anthony Rau papers
J. Walter Thompson Company. London Office. David Faulkner papers
J. Walter Thompson Company. London Office. Jack Cronin papers
J. Walter Thompson Company. London Office. Miles Colebrook papers
J. Walter Thompson Company. London Office. Print advertisements
J. Walter Thompson Company. London Office records
Collection Overview
Collection includes correspondence, policy manuals, presentation texts and designs and other printed materials that document JWT new business proposals for commercial, nonprofit and governmental institutions. Some of the proposals include marketing plans for flotation and privatization of nationalized industries. Companies represented include Barclays Bank, British Airways, British Rail, BUPA (British United Provident Association), Cancer Relief Macmillan Fund, CGL (Computer Games Limited), De Beers, Dunlop, Esso, Findus, Gatwick Airport, H.P. Bulmer, ICI Dulux, ITVA, Jaguar, Kodak, NatWest and Philips, as well as British governmental agencies including the Central Office of Information (later COI Communications), Home Office and Metrication Board. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Advertising; Advertising -- Great Britain; Advertising -- Great Britain -- History; Advertising agencies; Advertising agencies -- Great Britain; Advertising agencies -- Great Britain -- History; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; British Airways; De Beers Consolidated Mines; Dunlop Rubber Company; Esso Petroleum Company, ltd; Esso UK (Firm); Findus (Firm); Eastman Kodak Company
- General Files, 1957-1992 and undated; 1
  - 10 Questions to Ask New Prospects When Making Cold Calls, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Criteria for Selecting a Worldwide Agency, undated (Box 1)
  - JWT New Business Checklist for Winners, 1992 (Box 1)
  - JWT New Business Handbook, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Market for Electric Shavers in the United Kingdom, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - Market Modelling in Action, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Publicity handout packet, 1983 (Box 9)
  - Summary of the UK Baby Food Market, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Things We're Learning About Winning New Business, 1991 (Box 1)
- Prospect Files, 1946-1998 and undated; 2
  - Abbey National, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Activision--Advertising recommendations for the UK launch of River Raid, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Air India--The Best of All Possible Worlds, 1989 (Box 1)
  - ALCAN Aluminium (UK) Limited--ALCAN-JWT relationship and experience in Canada, 1981 (Box 1)
  - ALCAN Group of Companies--Advertising and promotional activities, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Alitalia, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Allied Breweries--Skol advertising recommendations, 1990 (Box 1)
  - APACS Cheque Card Committee, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Area Electricity Boards, 1989; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Argos, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Argos Distributors, 1989 (Box 1)
  - ASDA (grocery stores), 1994 (Box 1)
  - Associated Biscuits Limited--Review of the Biscuit Market in the UK, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Automobile Association--Survey of Motorists, 1965 (Box 1)
  - BACS Limited, 1989; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Barclays Bank--Agency brief appendix, undated (Box 1)
  - Barclays Bank--Attitudes towards Barclay Card, 19971 (Box 1)
  - Barclays Bank--Flight deck and miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - Bausch & Lomb (JWT Direct), 1990 (Box 1)
  - Beechams--Advertising Research Theory and Practice, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Belling, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Bernard Thorpe & Partners--London Stock Exchange flotation communications proposals, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Black & Decker, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Bondina (BDA) Limited--Preliminary report on the UK market for synthetic household cloths, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Bowater Zenith Windows, 1985 (Box 1)
  - BP Trading Limited, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Braun, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Brewers Society--Proposed advertising programme, 1947 (Box 1)
  - British Airways, 1995; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - British Airways--Reply to letter, 1973 (Box 1)
  - British Airways--Worldwide media planning guidelines, 1995 (Box 1)
  - British Poultry Meat Association, 1976 (Box 1)
  - British Rail, 1984 (Box 1)
  - British Rail Shipping Services, 1960, 1967; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - British Rail Shipping Services--Irish Sea Routes, undated (Box 2)
  - British Shoe Corporation--Television advertising (Manfield & Sons), 1958 (Box 2)
  - British Steel--Proposal for flotation advertising for privatisation of British Steel, 1988 (Box 2)
  - BSB (British Satellite Broadcasting)--JWT's View on the Opportunity, 1987 (Box 2)
  - BUPA (British United Provident Association), 1992 (Box 2)
  - BUPA (British United Provident Association)--Healthscope, 1989 (Box 2)
  - BUPA (British United Provident Association)--JWT: Some Questions Answered, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Burton Tailoring--An Approach to Advertising Strategy, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Cadbury Schweppes--Brand positioning (Suncrush, Kia Ora), 1973 (Box 2)
  - Canary Wharf, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Cancer Relief MacMillan Fund--MacMillan Nurse Appeal, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Cancer Relief MacMillan Fund--National Appeal, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Carteret Products--Sovol, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Central Office of Information (COI), 1994 (Box 2)
  - Central Office of Information (COI)--Recent Developments at JWT Limited, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Charities Aid Foundation, 1978 (Box 2)
  - City of Newcastle Upon Tyne, 1989; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Clarksons--Recommendations for a company image campaign, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Compaq Computer, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Computer Games Limited (CGL)--Frogger launch, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Computer Games Limited (CGL)--Video Games Qualitative Overview, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Cook Electric, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Cooks/BEA (British European Airways)--Cooks Silver Wing Holidays, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Curwin Poultry Limited, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Custom Interiors, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Cynamid Agricultural Division--Avenge 2, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Dae Health Laboratories, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Daily Telegraph, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Dearne Valley Partnership, 1992; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - DeBeers/AAC (Anglo American Corporation of South Africa), 1989; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Del Monte--Branding Fresh Fruit Across Europe, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Department of Employment/COI (Central Office of Information), 1985 (Box 2)
  - Department of Employment/COI (Central Office of Information)--The Future's Going to Work, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Department of Social Security/COI (Central Office of Information)--Advertising for Family Credit, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Department of Trade and Industry/COI (Central Office of Information), 1987 (Box 2)
  - Dimplex Heating Appliances, 1961-1962; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Distillers Company Limited--Brand Choice of Whisky in On-Licenses, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Dixon Group/Peter Morris--The Need for a Brand Authority in the Electrical Retailing Market, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Dunlop Rubber Company, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Dunlop Rubber Company--Research on Tyres (BMRB), 1964 (Box 3)
  - Dunlop Rubber Company--Tyre Companies Image Study, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Earth Centre, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Electricity Association, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Electricity Council, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Electricity Supply Industry, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Elida Gibbs--Denim fragrance, 1990 (Box 3)
  - ELS (Executive Leather Sofa), 1990 (Box 3)
  - Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Engineering Marketing Group--Making Engineering Matter, 1998 (Box 3)
  - English China Manufacturers Association--Proposals for research into the market for British Pottery (BMRB), 1957 (Box 3)
  - Esso, 1991; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Esso--JWT: The Quest for Quality, undated (Box 3)
  - Esso--JWT response on terms of business, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Esso--JWT response to invitation to bid on lubricants business, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Esso--JWT response to invitation to bid on retail, corporate, and lubricants business, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Euro Tunnel--Attitudes towards Eurotunnel, undated (Box 3)
  - Euro Tunnel--JWT European credentials, 1991 (Box 3)
  - European Commission (EC)--Ecolabeling UK strategy, 1992 (Box 3)
  - European Telecom/Racal Survey--Transforming a Joint Venture into a Winning Brand, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Eurostar--Cross Channel high-speed train service, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Evening Standard, 1992; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Findus (UK) Limited--Competitive review, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Findus (UK) Limited--Dinner Supreme, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Findus (UK) Limited--Pancakes Away Day, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Findus (UK) Limited--The Finest Food-Frozen brand review, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Findus (UK)/Nestle, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Fisher Price, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Florsheim Shoes--Men's footwear market, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Florsheim Shoes--Mens's shoe market advertising review, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Flour Advisory Bureau--Recommendation on the co-operative promotion of bread, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Forte Hotels, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Friskies Petcare, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Frito-Lay--The Jewel in the PepsiCo Crown, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Frizzell Group, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Galileo, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Gateway, 1989-1990; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Gatwick Airport (Duty-free shops), 1990 (Box 4)
  - Gatwick Airport (Duty-free shops), 1990 (Box 8)
  - Gatwick Airport (Duty-free shops), 1990 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Geest Prepared Produce, 1992 (Box 4)
  - General Council of the Bar, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Glenlivet Scotch Whisky, 1991 (Box 4)
  - GNI Limited, 1987 (Box 4)
  - Golden Wonder--Crisps, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Golden Wonder--Pots, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Golden Wonder--What Makes Wotsits So Wonderfully Wotsit?, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Goldsmith Jewelers (JWT Direct), 1990 (Box 7)
  - GPA Group (aircraft leasing), 1991 (Box 4)
  - Great Lakes Tourism (U.S.), 1990 (Box 4)
  - Hamfield Publications, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Harris Queensway, 1987 (Box 4)
  - Harveys of Bristol--Harveys Sherries in Europe, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Hawley's Toy Store, 1986, 1989; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Heineken, 1990; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Hilton International, 1992 (Box 4)
  - H.J. Heinz, 1990 (Box 4)
  - HM Treasury/British Telecom--BT Share Offer, 1991 (Box 4)
  - HM Treasury/British Telecom--BT Share Offer: Project Angle II, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Hoechst UK Agricultural Division, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Home Office/COI--Crime Prevention, 1987 (Box 4)
  - Home Office/COI--Partners Against Crime, undated (Box 4)
  - Home Office/COI--Police recriutment campaign, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Hoover International Appliances, 1997 (Box 4)
  - Hoseasons, 1992 (Box 4)
  - H.P. Bulmer--Soft drinks, 1994 (Box 4)
  - H.P. Bulmer--Strongbow cider, 1988 (Box 4)
  - H.P. Bulmer--Woodpecker, 1990 (Box 4)
  - ICI--Decorative paints, undated (Box 4)
  - ICI--Dulux, 1994 (Box 4)
  - ICI--Dulux: Project Shepherd, 1992 (Box 4)
  - ICI--Fibres (Tactel), 1987 (Box 4)
  - ICI--JWT presentations, 1987; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - ICI--Why Pay Pots for Paint?, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Irish Tourist Board, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Irish Tourist Board--Ireland: Where All the Time in the World Isn't Enough, 1988 (Box 5)
  - ITP Limited (publishing), 1985 (Box 5)
  - ITV Association--Never a Dull Moment, 1988 (Box 5)
  - ITV Association--Phase Two, 1989 (Box 5)
  - ITV Association--Time for Children, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Jaguar--Implications of Channel 4 terms of business, 1993 (Box 5)
  - Jaguar--Millward Brown presentation, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Jaguar--XJ Series, 1994 (Box 5)
  - Japan Festival, 1990 (Box 5)
  - John West Foods Limited, 1990 (Box 5)
  - JVC (UK) Limited, 1992 (Box 5)
  - JVC (UK) Limited--Brown Goods and Brand Values, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Kellogg--All-Bran: The Inside Story, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Kodak--Copy products, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Kodak--Ektaprint European launch, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Kwik-Fit (automotive services), 1989; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Levi Strauss--Advertising recommendations for Northern Europe, 1982 (Box 5)
  - London Brewers Council--Exhibition, 1946 (Box 5)
  - London Docklands Development Corporation, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Lotus (computer software), 1984 (Box 5)
  - Lowenbrau, 1990 (Box 5)
  - M&G plc, 1989; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Mansfield Breweries--Mansfield and Riding Bitters, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Maples Group, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Marks & Spencer, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Marlow Foods, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Mateus, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Mateus--Rose, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Mattesons Wall's Ltd., 1989 (Box 5)
  - Metrication Board, 1970; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - National Maritime Museum Greenwich, 1989 (Box 5)
  - National Power, 1989; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - NatWest (National Westminster Bank), 1989 (Box 6)
  - NatWest (National Westminster Bank)--Advertising: The Way Ahead, 1989 (Box 6)
  - NatWest (National Westminster Bank)--Centralised Media Management, 1988; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - NatWest (National Westminster Bank)--Cluster analysis, 1988 (Box 6)
  - NatWest (National Westminster Bank)--Competitive advertising review, personal sector, 1988 (Box 6)
  - NatWest (National Westminster Bank)--Creative, 1988 (Box 6)
  - NatWest (National Westminster Bank)--Research brief, 1989 (Box 6)
  - NatWest (National Westminster Bank)--Strategy, 1989; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - NCM Credit Insurance, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Nintendo/Mike Hayes--Creative Ninspiration, 1993 (Box 6)
  - Nuclear Electric, 1990-1992; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Nuclear Electric--Harnessing the Power of Communications 1991-1994 (Box 6)
  - Nuclear Electric--Project Fossil, 1990 (Box 6)
  - PageB (Proprietary Association of Great Britain), 1997 (Box 6)
  - Philips Electronics--Gemini video system UK launch (Box 6)
  - Philips Electronics--Laservision, 1980, 1982; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Philips Electronics--Laservision false purchase study, 1982 (Box 6)
  - Philips Electronics--Laservision launch, 1982 (Box 6)
  - Philips Electronics--Presentation supplement, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Philips Electronics--Qualitative investigation into Laservision, 1983 (Box 6)
  - Philips Electronics--VLP video disc system, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Polycell, 1988 (Box 6)
  - PowerGen (energy company), 1989 (Box 6)
  - Project Jason (financial services), 1990 (Box 6)
  - Thomson Holidays--You Don't Have to Hope for the Best, 1982 (Box 6)
  - Toshiba--Brown Goods and Brand Values, 1989 (Box 6)
  - Twelve Regional Electricity Companies of England and Wales--Flotation advertising, 1990; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - United States Travel Service--Tender, 1976 (Box 6)
  - Walker Brothers (Scotch whisky)--Project J (JWT Hamburg), 1988 (Box 6)